בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today’s דף daf is כ״ט Chaf Tet and
we are a little ahead, we pick up at the משנה. mishnah.
And we’re still dealing with scenarios about delivering a גט get to
a שליח, shaliach, and we’ve been using that, I mean, that’s given
us an opportunity to explore some interesting scenarios, most recently the guy
was left alive, can we assume he’s still alive when the גט
get is being delivered? And now we get to something that’s actually
quite central, both gets us back to בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, bifnei
nichtav uvifnei nechtam, don’t forget about that, and also, but’s also central
to the idea of the person’s status as our שליח. shaliach. So
let’s take a look.
המביא גט בארץ ישראל, Hamayvi get b'eretz yisrael, somebody brings a גט
get in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, וחלה, ve'chala, and he gets sick
and he can’t continue his שליחות, shlichus, his agency, הרי זה משלחו
ביד אחר, harei zeh m'shalcho b'yad acher, he appoints another person. You
don’t need a בית דין, Beis Din, presumably you don’t even need
witnesses, right, which is also an interesting question, right, where’s like, you
know, how do you bring evidence that this person has been appointed
as the שליח? shaliach? If there needs to be עדי קיום הדבר,
eidei kiyum hadavar, that’s a general question. If witnesses have to testify
to the delivery of the גט, get, you know, how can they
testify if they don’t know that these are the right parties? It’s
actually an interesting question in קידושין, kiddushin, you know, the places that
have the מנהג minhag of having like a דק תכיל, dek tichul,
which is like, you know, the כלה kallah wears like a veil
that’s like really a thick opaque type of a thing, so how
does the חתן chosson know who he’s marrying? It could be like
a whole רחל ולאה Rachel and Leah story. Anyway, so, so that’s
a question about, you know, if you have somebody who says they’re
an agent to give the גט, get, do you need there to
be witnesses that identify that person’s status, you know, so that you
can combine the testimonies, at least in theory, and know and have
evidence that the person actually was appropriate, you know, was a messenger
of the husband? So could be that the answer is no. I
mean, we haven’t seen that yet, but it could be and maybe
you don’t need it at all, you don’t need to have to
be able to string together that evidence. But B, it might be
that holding onto the גט get provides in itself sufficient evidence to
this person’s status. Of course, that would leave over the question about
the woman appointing a שליח, shaliach, because there’s no evidence that that
person has been appointed by the woman and that is going to
be an interesting question, to what degree do you need testimony to
whether the person has been appointed as a שליח? shaliach? So here,
this person, at least he is carrying a גט, get, we’ve never
mentioned yet that he needs any testimony, any witnesses to see his
appointment. And here he can go ahead and he can’t continue it
and he can find somebody else to take his place and without
a בית דין, Beis Din, maybe probably even without witnesses, from the
sense of the משנה, mishnah, go ahead and appoint somebody else to
take his place and to continue the שליחות. shlichus. So that’s what
the משנה mishnah says. הרי זה משלחו ביד אחר. Harei zeh m'shalcho
b'yad acher. ואם אמר לו טול לי הימנה חפץ פלוני, Ve'im amar
lo tul li heimena cheifetz ploni, but if the husband said to
the שליח, shaliach, when you give the גט, get, make sure you
get back from her a certain object of mine she’s been holding
onto, maybe using the גט get as a little leverage here, something,
not clear, we’ll see about that in the גמרא, Gemara, but when
you give her the גט get I want you to get back
an object she’s holding
onto, so לא ישלחנו ביד אחר, lo yishlachenu b'yad acher, then he
cannot give over his שליחות shlichus to another person. Why not? שאין
רצונו שיהא פקדונו ביד אחר, She'ein retzono sheyehei pikdono b'yad acher, it
is not the husband’s desire that his פקדון, pikadon, his, we went
for פקדון, pikadon, the object that’s being watched, there’s a technical term
for this, anyway,
that that object that is entrusted, that he’s entrusting to the שליח,
shaliach, he does not want somebody else to be handling it. Okay,
you cannot assume that just because I asked ראובן Reuven to get
back from me that prized painting that my wife was holding onto,
that I’d be okay with שמעון Shimon getting that back. I don’t
want my painting to be held by שמעון, Shimon, I only wanted
it to be held by ראובן. Reuven. Now the question is, is
this one שליחות shlichus or two שליחויות? shlichuyos? Right? Okay, so fine,
don’t get the painting back, but still deliver the גט, get, right,
and to what degree is getting the painting back conditioned, the גט
get conditioned on the right person getting the painting back? It sounds
from the משנה mishnah that it is. It doesn’t, it sounds like
don’t send the גט, get, why don't you just say send the
גט get but don’t get the object? Or maybe well then I
won’t have the leverage. But okay, but if I did send the
גט get through the שליח shaliach and he did give it, and
whether he did or didn’t get the object and I’m not happy
with what happened with the object, is it still a good גט
get or not? That’s not clarified in the משנה. mishnah. What were
you going to say? Yeah. So, so that’s the second part, but
the first part is that the שליח shaliach can appoint another שליח.
shaliach. So let’s take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב
כהנא חלה תנן, Amar Rav Kahana chala tenan, says רב כהנא, Rav
Kahana, חלה תנן, chala tenan, our משנה mishnah says if the שליח
shaliach got sick. So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, peshita, obviously, חלה
תנן, chala tenan, it says it in the משנה, mishnah, I know
how to read! Okay, but the obvious point is he’s underscoring that
that’s a serious condition of the משנה. mishnah. No, מהו דתימא, mahu
d'teima, I might have thought, הוא הדין אף על גב דלא חלה,
hu hadin af al gav d'lo chala, you know what, even if
the שליח shaliach didn’t get sick, he can appoint somebody in his
stead, והא דקתני חלה, ve'ha de'ka tani chala, even if he didn't
get sick too. Why did it say he got sick? Just to
give you a common scenario, why is he appointing somebody else? But
it's not requisite like, you know, it's not you're allowed to appoint
somebody in your stead for whatever reason. No, קמשמע לן. kamashma lan.
No, that's what Rav Chana is telling you as a משנה Mishnah
means it when it says חלה. chala. You're only allowed to appoint
a substitute if you cannot complete the שליחות shlichus yourself. Otherwise you're
not entitled to appoint one. So now we're going to have to
explore that. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So thank you so much. Okay, so קמשמע לן. kamashma lan. היכי
דמי, Heichi dami, what's the case? אי דאמר ליה הולך, Ei d'amar
lei holech, if he just said to him deliver this גט, get,
אף על גב דלא חלה נמי, af al gav d'lo chala nami,
it should be good even without getting sick. Okay, now we're saying
this because we're about to quote a ברייתא braisa and the word
חלה chala getting sick is not in the ברייתא. braisa. Okay, so
we're just anticipating a ברייתא braisa we're about to quote. So if
he just said deliver it, then he should be able to appoint
a substitute without getting sick. ואי דאמר ליה את הולך, V'ei d'amar
lei at holech, if he said I want you to deliver it,
you deliver this גט, get, so you seems to be only you,
אפילו חלה נמי לא, afillu chala nami lo, then even getting sick
in case of getting sick he should not be entitled to create
a substitute. Okay, as we're about to see. ואי רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל, V'ei Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, and if it's following the position
of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel who we are
about to see, אפילו חלה נמי לא, afillu chala nami lo, also
getting sick shouldn't matter. דתניא. D'tanya. So all that was a lead
in to allow us to quote the following ברייתא. braisa.
דתניא, D'tanya, הולך גט זה לאשתי, holech get zeh l'ishti, deliver this
גט get to my wife, הרי זה משלח ביד אחר, harei zeh
meshaleach b'yad acher, you're allowed to send it, you're allowed to give
it over to somebody else. So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma of
the ברייתא braisa says you do not need to get sick, you
just are basically permitted to appoint somebody in your stead. הרי זה
משלח ביד אחר. Harei zeh meshaleach b'yad acher.
Wait a
minute. את הולך גט זה לאשתי, At holech get zeh l'ishti, if
you say you deliver this גט get to my wife, הרי זה
לא ישלח ביד אחר, harei zeh lo yishlach b'yad acher, don't send
it through somebody else. So the משנה Mishnah feels that חלה chala
is immaterial, right, doesn't mention it as a condition. And the difference
is between whether you said deliver or you deliver. Okay, so that's
the focus of the משנה, Mishnah, the ברייתא. braisa. רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, בין כך ובין כך bein
kach u'vein kach אין שליח עושה שליח. ein shaliach oseh shaliach. Either
way, you're not entitled to appoint another שליח. shaliach. So רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says you can never do it.
The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma of the ברייתא braisa says that it
matters whether you said deliver or you deliver. Nobody brings in the
idea of getting sick as a condition. So you could make it
a debate. Right, you could say that our משנה Mishnah feels getting
sick is what's important and this ברייתא braisa feels otherwise. But the
גמרא Gemara is going to try to reconcile and has three possible
ways of reconciling the ברייתא braisa with the משנה. Mishnah. Let's take
a look. אי בעית אימא Ei bais eima says the גמרא, Gemara,
הולך והוא דחלה. holech v'hu d'chala. One way to read it is
the most narrow way. You're only allowed to make a שליח shaliach
if you have both conditions: what the ברייתא braisa says, that you
said deliver, you don't say you deliver, you say deliver, and in
addition only under the condition that he gets sick. Okay, that it's
impossible to do it himself. That's the narrowest read. ואי בעית אימא,
V'ei bais eima, and if you want you could say, I keep
on losing my place, one minute. הולך והוא דחלה. Holech v'hu d'chala.
ואי בעית אימא, Ei bais eima, את הולך וחלה שאני. at holech
v'chala shani. That's the most lenient read. Either is enough. Either you
say deliver, then you can make a שליח shaliach or even if
you said as the ברייתא braisa when the ברייתא braisa said you
deliver you're not allowed to make a שליח, shaliach, the ברייתא braisa
would admit that if you got sick you are allowed. Okay, so
that's the most lenient read. A שליח shaliach to make a שליח
shaliach either if he didn't say the word you and even if
he said the word you, getting sick gives him that permission. ואי
בעית אימא, V'ei bais eima, and if you want and this is
just a variation of what we just said, ואי בעית אימא רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל היא, v'ei bais eima Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel hi,
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel who says doesn't matter
whether you said deliver or you deliver you can't, that's only the
default.
וחלה שאני, V'chala shani, but when you get sick you're allowed to.
Okay, so basically the last two of the three readings said even
in the cases that the ברייתא braisa identifies whether תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma or רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel that you're
not allowed to make a שליח, shaliach, even if it was a
case like you make it, when you get sick that gives you
the then you are allowed. Okay, you I mean you deliver when
you get sick. And again, it's not like there's some special הלכה
למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai about a שליח shaliach getting sick or
about you know or saying you as opposed to deliver. It seems
that it's all a question about whether it is you know implicitly
in the husband's assignment of agency or not, like what the husband
wanted. You know you could sort of say like הקפדה דבעל, hakpada
d'baal, but sometimes the הקפדה דבעל hakpada d'baal is like an extraneous
type of a thing. Like you know he just has some weird
concern that he you know that he doesn't want things to happen
under certain circumstances. Like we had a case for example whatever anyway.
But here it seems like it's a basic question of
under what conditions is the שליח shaliach empowered. Right, so do we
assume that when he says you deliver, he specifically wants to only
to say you have to be the one and not somebody else
and that's the very nature of the שליחות. shlichus. Okay, on the
other
hand we... So therefore, if it's not going to be possible otherwise,
the guy got sick, then that would be an exception and he
would allow for that to be handed over. And that's the idea
of חלה שאני. chola shani. Okay, so the חלה שאני chola shani
and the את הולך at holech are basically saying we're trying to
understand under what circumstances is the husband like, you know, is the
husband empowering the agency? Right? Is he prepared to have that agency
transferred over? And maybe under the normal case we would say no,
or certainly if he said, "you deliver," we would say no. But
ultimately he's more interested in getting the גט get delivered, so if
there's no other choice, if it's חלה chola he would want it.
Okay, well חלה chola is not just חלה.
chola. Right, it would be another אונס oness as well, any other
circumstance in which the שליח shaliach could not reasonably do it. Right,
exactly.
I guess it's an interesting question, which is what if it's not
an אונס oness but what if the שליח shaliach like refuses, you
know, like he change his mind, he whatever? It's like, yeah, I
just don't want a schlepp, I don't, whatever, I have too many
things I have to do today, I'm sorry, I'm not doing it.
It's not an אונס, oness, he could do it, okay? But ultimately
if the husband wants the גט get delivered, right, and that's more
important, right? So that's an interesting question, which I don't know the
answer. Okay, anyway so that's the issue. The issue is is that
with
חלה, chola, חלה chola might be דווקא davka in our משנה, mishna,
but that might be an allowance to a case when he said
את הולך. at holech. Okay, now the גמרא gemara continues.
Okay, תנן, tnan, we taught in a משנה: mishna: המביא גט בארץ
ישראל וחלה—our hamevi get be'eretz yisrael vechala משנה—הרי זה משלחו ביד אחר.
ורמינהו, uraminihu, now I'm going to challenge this idea that you can
appoint somebody else. Whatever the conditions are. You got sick, you didn't
say את, at, you can appoint somebody else. We have another
תני tani משנה: mishna אמר לשנים, amar lishnayim, says to two people,
תנו
גט לאשתי, tenu get l'ishti, give a get to my wife, או
לשלושה, o lishlosha, כתבו גט ותנו לאשתי, kitvu get utnu l'ishti, or
to three, right, and give a get to my wife, הרי אלו
יכתבו ויתנו. harei elu yichtevu veyitnu. They have to be the ones
to write it and give it, they cannot appoint somebody else.
אינהו אין, inhu in, they yes, אבל שליח לא, aval shaliach lo,
they can't appoint a שליח. shaliach. And what's the idea behind this?
Let's start with the idea about the difference between two and three.
If he said to three people, "give a get to my wife,"
okay, so three people is understood to be a בית דין. beit
din. And "give a get" would mean supervise that a get be
given to my wife. And therefore they can appoint somebody to write
it. So that's the case which starts off as the case that
allows them to appoint it to somebody else. You have three people,
they're a בית דין, beit din, he says, "give it to my
wife," they would be allowed to have somebody write it. But if
he says to those three, "write it and give it to my
wife," then we assume that that means not just supervise, that he's
telling them they have to write it. So they cannot appoint somebody
else. Okay, that's just the assumption. "Give it" means supervise, make sure
it gets given. "Write it and give it" means you have to
write
it. Okay? And give it also. Right, they have to be the
שליח shaliach for כתיבה ketiva and the שליח shaliach presumably for נתינה.
netina. We'll see about that in a minute, but yes. Okay. So
if he says to two, now if he just says to two,
"give it to my wife," so why doesn't "give it" mean see
that it gets given? No, that also they also have to write
it themselves, because even if he means see that it gets given,
when if unless it's a בית דין, beit din, you can't give
over like the responsibility to, you know, to to take like the
general responsibility that be given. Anything other than a בית דין beit
din you can only be appointing an agent. So if he says
to two "give it," that means he's appointing them as an agent
and basically the presumption of this משנה mishna: is, the way the
גמרא gemara is understanding it, is that an agent, a שליח shaliach
cannot make a שליח. shaliach. Okay, an agent cannot pass it over.
So if you say to two, they're just two agents, they're just
two שלוחים, shluchim, and therefore they can't pass it over, they have
to write it and give it themselves. If you say to three,
if you have a בית דין, beit din, a בית דין beit
din can make a שליח shaliach for you. So if you said
תנו, tenu, they can make a שליח shaliach for you because now
you're you're telling them "oversee it." But if you say כתבו, kitvu,
then you're telling them "write it yourselves." Okay? So that's again, the
basic point is,
כתבו ותנו kitvu utnu is understood to mean write it yourself, write
it and give it yourselves.
Okay?
תנו tenu means see that it gets given. See that it gets
given. Okay, that's the difference. So if it's a בית דין beit
din and you said תנו, tenu, they don't have to do it
themselves. If you said כתבו ותנו, kitvu utnu, they do. But the
משנה mishna says if it's two people, even if you said see
that it gets given, they gotta do it themselves. Why? Because a
שליח shaliach can't make a שליח. shaliach. The only person that can
appoint an agent is a בית דין beit din or the husband.
Okay, a בית דין beit din on behalf of the husband. Okay,
but two people, even תנו, tenu, they have to do it themselves
because they cannot appoint a שליח shaliach in their stead. They're only,
so that is the רישא reisha of that משנה. mishna So let's
take a look. Yes.
I guess we said this before, but it it seems a little
odd. I mean, it's all very technical and the weight of the
matter and everything. Right. And the idea that you can just effect
a גט get and the whole writing and giving and everything just
by giving an instruction. Right. In in some...
Well, what would you need the husband to do more than instruct?
I mean, he's gonna have to, right, what, he has to write
it himself? He has to deliver it himself? I mean he's gonna...
Right, exactly. You're saying like the fact that all he needs to
do is say those magic words, right, one time, right, I mean,
but isn't that true also like you talk about somebody appointing power
of attorney, although I guess there, you know, you need a serious
document written out and you made, right, you know, it's not just
a verbal instruction, right? Like you might need, right, you're thinking why
doesn't the husband at least have to sign something appointing the בית
דין? Beis Din? Right, it is interesting. Right, it's just those magic
words once. Alright, so that's the challenge that this משנה mishna. makes
it sound like the only people that can be given over the
ability to pass on the agency is a בית דין. Beis Din.
Okay, and then only if you say the right words, תנו, tnu,
meaning see that it gets given. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: הני אין, hani in, they yes, אבל שליח לא, aval
shaliach lo, סתמא שליח, stama shaliach,
meaning if it's not the בית דין, Beis Din, if it's two
people, certainly if it's only one, you can't give over the agency
of the writing and the giving of the גט. get. So what's
the difference? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, התם טעמא מאי? משום בזיונא דבעל.
הכא בעל לא קפיד. Hasam ta'ama mai? Mishum bizyona de-ba'al. Hacha ba'al
lo kapid.
There it's because of the embarrassment of the husband. Here, the husband
doesn't mind. Now, what makes the כתבו תנו גט kitvu s'nu get
more of an issue of the embarrassment of the husband than in
our case? And we didn't say that there he, that here he
minds but in our case he doesn't. So רש״י Rashi says it
has to do with the difference of the writing. That there's a
presumption that the husband would write his own גט. get. It's quite
fascinating. Nowadays nobody would presume anybody would write their own גט. get.
Oh, you gotta get a special סופר, sofer, etc. But if you
think about it, if all a גט get says is, think about
a classic גט: get: הרי את מותרת לכל אדם, harei at muteses
l'chol adam, right? I mean when we say, for example, it's true,
you need the name and you need the date and you need
לשמה lishma and all those types of things, right? But if the
idea fundamentally is an expression of the husband's will, like when the
גמרא Gemara says, you know what a standard שטר מכר shtar mecher
is if I'm selling you my field? שדי נתונה לך sadi nesuna
lach or שדי מכורה לך. sadi mechura lach. That's the field, it's
the whole שטר, shtar, it's an expression of my will. Now presumably
you need to say exactly what field we're talking about and those
types of things. But anyway, but if there's a presumption, I mean,
the גמרא Gemara sort of said it before in terms of the
debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, does
the וכתב ve-chasav of the פסוק pasuk הבעל קאי ha-ba'al kai or
הסופר קאי? ha-sofer kai? But the way רש״י Rashi expresses it is
that there's somehow this societal presumption that the husband is going to
be writing the גט, get, and therefore anytime he's giving it over
to somebody else, it's a little embarrassing. Now you could also say
that the, it's the very fact that he's divorcing his wife, maybe
he doesn't want to make that public. Anyway, there's something here that
we presume he wants to be keeping a little bit quiet. And
therefore when it starts at the basic agency of the writing of
the גט, get, when we're starting at that stage in the process,
we presume he wants to keep things quiet. And anything less than
a בית דין, Beis Din, when he explicitly says אתם בית דין
atem Beis Din to sort of a public thing and I'm giving
it over to a public institution and I'm saying תנו, tnu, which
means oversee it, not do it yourself, anything less than that we
assume he wants to keep it quiet and he doesn't want to
pass down. Okay. But it's all just arbitrary. There's nothing intrinsic that
would prevent him from doing it in this case. And therefore in
a case where we don't presume he wants to keep it quiet
or there's, anyway, there's like no choice, he's sending a גט, get,
he's delivering it to another location, it's about the delivery of the
גט, get, right? So in that type of a case, of course
you gotta send it through somebody else. You know, clearly, so there's
nothing to be embarrassed about. It's the normal way you do is
you deliver it through, you know, somebody who's traveling to that location.
There's no presumption that that case he wants to keep quiet or
that he would have any concern with handing it over. Okay, so
that's basically, but it seems to be one like a very secondary
type of an issue, nothing intrinsic to the case itself. The next
answer is more interesting, okay? So it says like
this: רבא אמר, Rava amar,
now רבא Rava says a more interesting answer: משום דמילי נינהו, mishum
de-mili ninhu, because these are just words. ומילי, u-mili,
isn't that what Eliza Doolittle says? "Words, words,
words"? Okay, ומילי לא מימסרן לשליח, u-mili lo mimsaran l'shaliach, and words
are not given over to a שליח, shaliach, which means this gets
to the problem a little bit that Dov was referring to before,
that שליחות, shlichus, it's all very ephemeral, this whole thing is just
words. Write a גט get for my wife. I made you an
agent, there is nothing that concretizes your
agency. Write a גט get for my wife. So if there's nothing
that concretizes, the only thing that gives him that status is he
received the direct... Instruction from me. Okay, and therefore there's nothing that
allows, sort of there's no mechanics for him to transfer that over.
It's all too abstract. Okay, and there's no physical גט. get. But
if I give him the גט get and say deliver this גט
get to my wife, this גט get is the embodiment of his
agency. We talked before about maybe it's also the testimony to his
status. But it's the embodiment of his agency. Whoever is carrying the
גט get is clearly the person empowered to deliver it. So it
represents that agency and therefore he can give it over and appoint
somebody else. So again, the נפקא מינה nafka mina of this would
be the woman who makes a שליח, shaliach, that she cannot make
a שליח shaliach to receive the גט. get. Okay, or the other
נפקא מינה nafka mina is even if the husband announces in the
case of the writing, I don't care, you can go ahead and
appoint whoever you want, that doesn't matter to me, right, presumably it
would not work because the only thing that a שליח shaliach can
make a שליח shaliach has nothing to do with the הקפדה, hakpadah,
it's only the case of the delivery of the גט get that
the husband is sending. The writing of the גט get you couldn't
do it, the woman's receiving of the גט get a שליח shaliach
couldn't make a שליח, shaliach, only the case of the delivery of
the גט. get. Okay, ומילי לא מימסרן לשליח. u-milei lo mimsran l'shaliach.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu, here what would
be a difference between them? איכא בינייהו לשליח מתנה. ika beinaihu l'shaliach
matanah. So again, I think it would be more interesting to talk
about a case if the husband isn't מקפיד makpid or a שליח
shaliach of receiving the גט get that the wife could, that שליח
shaliach make a שליח, shaliach, but the גמרא Gemara also says what
about a שליח shaliach to write a שטר shtar to gift a
plot of land to somebody. Okay, so in that case, there's no
ביזיון. bizayon. What do I care? It's not like there's private aspects
of a גט. get. So that's the case I'm gifting a plot
of land and I say to one person write it, can he
appoint another person to write it and give it. Okay, ובפלוגתא דרב
ושמואל. u-v'flugta d'Rav u-Shmuel. It's the debate of Rav and Shmuel. רב
אמר מתנה אינה
כגט. Rav amar matanah einah k'get. It's not like a גט get
and if you make a שליח shaliach to write a שטר מתנה
shtar matanah they can make another שליח. shaliach. ושמואל אמר מתנה הרי
היא כגט. u-Shmuel amar matanah harei hi k'get. It's the exact same
thing because it doesn't matter, it's not about his embarrassment, it's about
a שליחות shlichus that has no physical embodiment. Okay, and this is
really interesting, right, it gets to the idea that a person's status
is all very abstract, there's nothing that represents it, there's no שטר
shtar of שליחות, shlichus, there's nothing, so therefore can he appoint it,
can he go ahead and transfer it to somebody else? Also an
interesting question about how much that שליח shaliach to get his status
needs that direct contact from the husband. Does he need to hear
the appointment from the husband? Can you have a מינוי שליחות שלא
בפניו? minui shlichus shelo b'fanav? Right, that's an interesting question because I
say, this happens by the way by מכירת חמץ. mechirat chametz. Okay,
you know, can somebody say to me, you know, I'm appointing the
rabbi to be my שליח, shaliach, go when you see the rabbi
in שול, shul, go ahead and give him the two dollars or
whatever it is, sign the document, I am appointing him not in
his presence, I am appointing him to be my שליח shaliach to
sell the חמץ. chametz. Like do you need to be present in
order to make a שליח shaliach or so on. So what exactly
is needed to create that, there's no קנין kinyan that's done. The
רמב"ן Ramban actually, רמב"ם Rambam actually says that some people had a
מנהג minhag to do a קנין, kinyan, like a קנין סודר kinyan
sudar to concretize it, right? But again, like there's nothing, there's no
act that's done that concretizes him, there's nothing that represents the identity
and therefore the גמרא Gemara says it's intrinsically hard to or not
possible without a גט, get, without something physical to pass over. Okay,
and that is the position of what do you call. Now the
only exception of רבא. Rava. The only exception would be the בית
דין. Beis Din. If you said the בית דין Beis Din give
it, so then the בית דין Beis Din is different because somehow
there's an idea as a public institution, you're not just making them
their agent, they somehow can take on a responsibility, sort of like
the idea you know you can give over your debts to be
collected by בית דין Beis Din and that avoids the שמיטה shemittah
problem. You know that somehow בית דין, Beis Din, if you can,
they can't on their own decide they're going to get a גט
get delivered to her husband. You know that's part of the whole
עגונה agunah problem, right, is that the whole power is, the whole
thing is empowered, you know, it's all the husband's power, the בית
דין Beis Din is not empowered to deliver a גט, get, right?
There are some societies in which the courts in the end issues
the divorce. You have to bring it to court but in the
end it's not the husband or the wife but the court that
issues it. But here, while the husband starts as the one empowered,
he can somehow transfer that power and then the court is appointing
a שליח shaliach because they're now empowered by the husband to see
that it gets given, but they're not actually, that's a different role.
They're not actually the husband's agent. They're operating somehow as a court
that needs that to be empowered but now they're operating as a
court and they can appoint an agent to deliver it. Okay, so
that's the exception, says רבא. Rava. A court can go ahead and
then they're making a שליח. shaliach. They're not passing on an agency,
they're making a שליח. shaliach. But if you're an agent, you cannot
pass on that agency. Okay, very central idea. Now the גמרא Gemara
continues, ואם אמר לו טול הימנה חפץ פלוני. v'im amar lo tulo
heimena chafetz ploni. Now if he says to the שליח, shaliach, when
you deliver the גט, get, I want you to go ahead and
to get an object back from her. Then you cannot make another
שליח shaliach because he doesn't want somebody else to hold on to
that to that treasured painting. So now the question is: okay, but
how much does that affect the the שליחות shlichus on the גט?
get? So let's take a look. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish,
said Reish Lakish: כאן שנה רבי, Kan shana Rabbi, here Rabbi taught:
אין השואל רשאי להשאיל ואין השוכר רשאי להשכיר. Ein hasho'el rashai lehash'il
ve'ein hasocher rashai lehaskir. אשאיל, Ash'il, excuse me.
A a borrower cannot, I lent you my my rake, you can't
go ahead and lend it to somebody else, I'm not in you
know, and if I rented you my car you or rented you
my apartment, you can't sublet it. Okay, because we said in the
משנה Mishna that you have to assume that the person does not
want, he wants just because he wants you to watch his object
doesn't mean he wants somebody else to watch his object.
So אמר ליה רבי יוחנן, Amar lei Rabbi Yochanan, so Rabbi Yochanan
said: זו אפילו תינוקות של בית רבן יודעין. Zo afilu tinokos shel
beis raban yode'in. Even like even like you know first graders know
that. That's not a חידוש, chiddush, everybody knows that principle. That's not
the חידוש chiddush of the משנה. Mishna The חידוש chiddush of the
משנה Mishna. isn't that we we presume that you don't want somebody
else to use your object. You know of course if you only
said you can borrow it or you watch it, it doesn't mean
you're entitled to let somebody else do it. That's not the חידוש.
chiddush. אלא, Ella, by the way besides what we get onto what
he says is the חידוש, chiddush, I would say more than that.
It's one thing to say that if I'm asking you I mean
I don't know I guess this could go both ways, but intuitively
I would say if I lend you an object or rent it
to you where you're actually using it, right, whenever you use it
and you're you know getting benefit or whatever, you know it risks
damaging it or so on your primary focus is on the benefit
you're getting out of it not on the protection of the object,
so then I would I would think I would be most מקפיד
makpid I don't think somebody else could borrow it. Maybe somebody else
won't be as careful as you, right, when they're you know renting
my subletting my apartment or borrowing my rake or whatever it is.
It's different I'm not sure I would have said it's the same
if I said I want you to watch my object, right? Then
I could say you know unless there's a reason to think that
another person is irresponsible, if their primary responsibility they're accepting upon themselves
is to protect the object, right, so maybe maybe I could more
presume that a normal type of a person barring special circumstances, you
know I might not have as much הקפדה. hakpada. I don't know
you could argue the opposite. If I'm focused on watching the object
maybe I'm very מקפיד makpid who watches it. So it could go
either way but it is interesting that the גמרא Gemara immediately compares
the cases of watching and protecting to borrowing. Yes Jenna?
It says that the borrower is more responsible because it's a job
to watch.
Right exactly. Well that's actually interesting, not necessarily. Sometimes the people that
borrow, I mean that's the whole סוגיא sugya in בבא מציעא, Bava
Metzia, it actually winds up that people that borrow tend to be
more responsible because of the benefit they're deriving even though it's true
their relationship to it is less from their perspective is less primarily
about their duty of care. That's a good yeah that's true. Okay
anyway but he says look all of that is obvious. That's you
don't need that's A it's in the משנה, Mishna B you don't
need anybody to tell me that. That's not the חידוש chiddush of
the משנה. Mishna, So what is the חידוש? chiddush? אלא Ella here's
the חידוש. chiddush. זימנין דגיטא נמי לא הוי. Zimnin degitta nami lo
havei. There's
the חידוש chiddush is is that there're circumstances in which because this
I wanted only this שליח shaliach to handle the painting, there's times
in which the גט get will be invalid if he goes ahead
and hands over that responsibility. Let's take a look. דנעשה כמי שאומר
לו, Dena'aseh kemi she'omer lo, it's like he said to him: אל
תגרשה אלא בבית, Al tgareshah ella babayis, וגרשה בעליה. Vegershah be'aliyah. He
made a condition about what are the circumstances he wanted the גט
get handed over. If he said I only want you to divorce
her in a house and he divorced her in the you know
on the ground floor and he divorced her on the second floor.
אל תגרשה אלא בימין, Al tgareshah ella biyamin, I want you to
give it to her with your right hand, וגרשה בשמאל, Vegershah bismol,
and he gave it to her with his left hand. Okay this
that's a case, it's a crazy condition but it nevertheless that would
it would it would make the giving of the גט get limited
to those cases. וכולי האי, Vechulei hai, okay so therefore what he
is saying is the point of the משנה Mishna. is because you
wanted the גט, get, you wanted the object and you sounded like
you were going to you know make sure you got the object
before you gave the גט, get, you use the גט get as
some leverage to get the object or something, that maybe the whole
שליחות shlichus depends on you being the one to receive it and
I won't trust somebody else to receive it and I won't want
the גט get given under conditions in which I can't be confident
that the right person is getting my object back, right, and that's
what it really does sound like in the משנה. Mishna So now
the גמרא Gemara is going to explain that it depends on the
circumstances. Let's take a look. היכא דנפק קלא אפי, Heicha denafak kala
appei,
when the woman comes out to greet the שליח, shaliach, ויהיבא ליה
חפץ, Veyahiba lei chefetz, why exactly he said that it's a little
funny but anyway, and
and she went ahead and she like gave him, she was so
eager to get the גט get she proferred the חפץ chefetz to
him right at the outset, right, והדר שקלה מיניה גיטא, Vehadar shakla
minei gitta, and then she took the גט get from him, כולי
עלמא לא פליגי דגיטא גטא מעליא הוי, Kulei alma lo peligi degitta
gitta ma'alya havei, that it's a good גט, get, okay, because he
got the object before giving it back. Now כי פליגי, Ki peligi,
when do they debate and we'll see who the פליגי peligi is,
let's but let's take a look. היכא דאמר לה: Heicha de'amar lah:
שקולי מינך חפץ והדר הב לה גיטא. Shekuli minach chefetz vehadar hav
lah gitta.
So really it has less to do with that she came to
greet the שליח shaliach and more what he said. If he just
said get the you know give her the גט get and get
the object then it's okay. It seems like it's two separate agencies
and they're not dependent one on the other. But if he formulated
it as get the object and then give her the גט, get,
okay, then it's clear that he wants to make sure the object
gets first and he's seeing them as conditional one on the other.
In that case, דאזיל איהו ויהבי לה גיטא והדר שקיל מינה חפץ,
d'azil ihu v'yahvei lah gita v'hadar shakil minah chafetz, and he reversed
the order. He first gave her the גט, get, lost his leverage,
and then he got the object, okay, so רבי יוחנן פוסל בו
וכל שכן בשלוחו. Rabbi Yochanan posul bo v'chol shekein b'shlucho. So in
that case there's a debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש
לקיש. Resh Lakish. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says in that case it's
not good if he did it, does it, and certainly if his
שליח shaliach does it it's no good. וריש לקיש מכשיר בשלוחו וכל
שכן בו. V'Resh Lakish machshir b'shlucho v'chol shekein bo.
And ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says, no, even in that case it's
a separate שליחות shlichus and it's good if he does it and
certainly it's okay and and it's certainly it's okay if the שליח
shaliach does it and reverses the order and certainly if he does
it it's okay. The גט get is not dependent under those cases.
Now, one minute. What have we said exactly? Because the משנה Mishna.
actually seems to say that this seems to say there's no difference.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, you know, in either case if he
did the order wrong it's okay, whether if he did the order
wrong it's no good, him and the שליח, shaliach, which seems to
be if you did the order right it would be okay even
to have somebody else do it. Meaning בו, bo, meaning not the
husband. בו bo meaning שליח shaliach one. Right? Is everybody let let
me step back. I I might have rushed into this, not explained
this sufficiently. So the point is, it's what what's being said now
is is that there are cases where hold on one second.
Okay.
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish seems to have said that this just teaches
you that husband that people don't want their object kept in the
hands of other people. So ריש לקיש Resh Lakish seems to say
that the שליחות shlichus of the גט get was not dependent on
the act of of of watching the object and it's just a
completely separate concern. So the גט get will always be good. There's
just a point whether you're allowed to have somebody else receive the
object for you, which was not פשט pshat of the משנה, Mishnah
but that's what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish said. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says that's not פשט pshat of the משנה. Mishnah, That's obvious. פשט
pshat of the משנה Mishnah. is is that the גט get is
actually dependent on the right person, on receiving the object, that he
really cares about that and he's making the גט get dependent on
that. So the question therefore is, the גמרא Gemara says, well, listen,
if the husband just said get the you know get the object,
get the גט, get, give her give her the גט, get, get
the object, so and he said get the object after give her
the גט, get, so then he doesn't mean to use the גט
get as leverage and everybody would agree that the גט get is
always going to be good. The question is when he says get
the object and then give her the גט, get, where it sounds
like very much he's very מקפיד makpid not only that he wants
his object, but that the גט get should be dependent on the
right receiving of the object. So in that case when he said
that order, that's where ריש לקיש Resh Lakish would say, I don't
care, I see them as independent, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would
say, no, the actual giving of the גט get is dependent on
on it being done in the right way, on on the getting
the object being done in the right way. So ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish says, we'll just read the last one, מכשיר בשלוחו וכל שכן
בו. machshir b'shlucho v'chol shekein bo. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says, I
don't care, even if he said get the object and then give
her the גט, get, it is not dependent, the גט get is
not dependent on the getting of the object. So if the even
if the שליח shaliach of the שליח shaliach is what it means,
even if the שליח shaliach of the שליח shaliach is the one
to receive it and certainly if he's the one to receive it
and even if he does it in the wrong order, that first
he gave her the גט get before getting the object, okay, none
of that matters, I it's not the כשרות kashrus of the גט
get is not dependent on the right receiving of the object. That's
what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish is saying. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is
saying, no, when he said that particular order, get the object and
then give the גט, get, the כשרות kashrus of the גט get
is dependent on the right receiving of the order. And therefore it's
פוסל בו וכל שכן בשלוחו. posel bo v'chol shekein b'shlucho. Now what
does פוסל בו posel bo mean? When when is it not good?
What's not good is even if the first שליח shaliach does it
in the wrong order, the first שליח shaliach first gave the גט
get and then got the object, so in the end he got
the object, it's invalid, because at the moment that the גט get
was given that was not the way the husband wanted the גט
get to be given. You're losing your leverage, right? So at the
moment the גט get was given that's an invalid giving of the
גט. get. Is that clear? If he says, get the object and
then give her the גט, get, so even if the same agent
reversed the order, it's invalid because when he gave the גט get
he was I was afraid that he was going to risk getting
the object back. Okay, and certainly if the שליח shaliach if he
made somebody else do it would it be invalid. Okay, so רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, ריש לקיש Resh Lakish basically say they're always independent.
Now, the question is, but the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* makes it sound
that it's the שליח shliach *Shaliach*, right? That's the
משנה mishna *Mishnah* makes it sound the problem is not that he
did it wrong, the משנה mishna? *Mishnah* makes it sound that there's
a problem with the שליח shliach *Shaliach* doing it, right? That if
he says get the object, he can't make a שליח shliach *Shaliach*.
So the way תוספות *Tosafot* reads רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, when he
says פסול בו ופסול בשלוחו *posel bo u-fasul bishlucho*, it means if
you, agent number one, did it in the wrong order, even though
you got the object in the end, it's no good. And certainly
if you made an agent, then even if that agent did it
in the right order, it's no good because I certainly don't want
anybody else handling my object. Okay, so רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says
two things. Number one is if he says a particular order, then
the כשרות *kashrut* of the גט get, *Get* is dependent on getting
the object back in the right way, number one. And number two,
there are two ways you can invalidate the כשרות *kashrut* of the
גט get, *Get*. You could not get the object back in the
right way. What are the two ways of not getting it back
in the right way? You yourself do it but you do it
in the wrong order, or you get somebody to do it in
your stead and I never wanted anybody else to handle my object.
And that's how רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* reads the משנה mishna *Mishnah*,
which I think is a pretty good read of the משנה mishna.
*Mishnah*. Yes.
In the real world actually, you know, if two people want leverage
over each other, the way you do it is you take a
third neutral party. I'm not giving you the גט get *Get* until
you give me the painting. I'm not giving you the painting until
you give me the גט get. *Get*. So then we'll both give
it to somebody we both trust, Rick, so then we both, so
then, so that's actually the way it would
work according to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*.
That's interesting. Right.
Well, no, but he could, but it would work if the husband
agreed to those conditions. Right. I understand. The reason this is different
is because the husband has unilateral power. In your scenario, both parties
have like equal sort of power in the exchange, right?
Well, they kind of do, she has the leverage of holding the
painting.
Right, well that's true, you're right. He actually sent, right, you're right.
If, why is there a case where it just says
if the agent gave the גט get *Get* and didn't receive the
object back, then the גט get *Get* is not valid?
That also, that's obvious, but according to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, according
to ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* it doesn't matter, they're always independent. According
to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* that's obvious. The חידוש *chiddush* here is
that for even if he did get the object back, if he
got it back after having lost his leverage, it's no good for
רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*.
That part is what I'm trying to, what's the big deal?
The deal is at the moment that the גט get *Get* was
given, even though a minute later he got the object, at the
moment the גט get. *Get* was given, I was like, ah, you're
not going to get the painting, right? So therefore the גט get
*Get* was invalid at that moment. It doesn't matter five minutes later,
two seconds later he got the painting. At the moment it was
given, he was violating my desire. He was risking not getting the
painting back.
He wasn't fulfilling the שליחות shlichus, *shlichut*.
He has to, and it's like he has an object that was
handed over to him for a particular purpose.
Right, has to use it in that way, exactly. Okay, let's look
at the next משנה Mishna. *Mishnah*. Okay, so that's if it's being
brought in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel *Eretz Yisrael* where there's no בפני
נכתב ובפני נחתם b'fanai nichtav u'b'fanai nechtam. *befanei nechtav u-vifanei nechtam* and
it gets to the heart of the question about under what conditions
can a שליח shliach *Shaliach* pass on his שליחות shlichus, *shlichut* and
this very important idea of מילי לא מימסרן לשליח mili lo mimseran
l'shaliach. *mili lo mimsran leshalia*, words are not given over to be
handed over to someone else, that abstract appointment. Now we turn to
the בפני נכתב b'fanai nichtav. *befanei nechtav*. המביא גט get ממדינת הים
*Hameivi Get mimedinat hayam*, bringing a גט get *Get* from overseas, וחלה
*ve-chala*, and gets sick. עושה שליח shliach בבית דין ומשלחו *oseh shaliach
beveit din umeshalcho*, so we've already decided that you can go ahead
and appoint to somebody in your place when you get sick, but
now there's a problem, you have to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם
b'fanai nichtav u'b'fanai nechtam *befanei nechtav u-vifanei nechtam* and your שליח shliach
*shaliach* who's taking your place won't be able to say it. So
what you have to do is you have to do it and
get a בית דין beis din. *beit din*, which is pretty much
evidence that you have to do בפני נכתב b'fanai nichtav, *befanei nechtav*
in front of a בית דין beis din *beit din*, which is
debated in the beginning of the first פרק *perek*, and testify in
front of the בית דין beis din בפני נכתב b'fanai nichtav. ובפני
נחתם *beit din befanei nechtav u-vifanei nechtam* and then appoint another שליח
shliach *shaliach* and then that שליח shliach? *shaliach* can just come and
say I can't say בפני נכתב b'fanai nichtav *befanei nechtav* but I
was appointed by the בית דין beis din. *beit din*, the בית
דין Beis Din *beit din* in such and such a city heard
the original שליח shliach *shaliach*'s testimony of בפני נכתב b'fanai nichtav. ובפני
נחתם *befanei nechtav u-vifanei nechtam*. Okay. ואומר לפניהם בפני נכתב b'fanai nichtav,
ובפני נחתם *ve-omer lifnehem befanei nechtav u-vifanei nechtam*, ואין שליח shliach אחרון
צריך שיאמר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם *ve-ein shaliach acharon tzarich she-yomar befanei
nechtav u-vifanei nechtam*, אלא אומר שליח בית דין
shliach beis din אני *ela omer shaliach beit din ani*, I'm an
agent of the court. Okay and that's okay. So this is sort
of presuming though that this is a בית דין Beis Din, *beit
din* that
sort of meets where you can find them and you could go
back. Yeah, I mean, right, that's a good point, right, it does
presume, right, not just you get three people together. Right, it's an
interesting point though, maybe, but I'm
not, yeah,
I don't know, it's a good question. I mean, you know, you're
getting to that question again about being able to prove everything, which
is an issue that we raised, right, about like how can the
chain of evidence as it were be proven? Yeah, but it's not
clear, yeah, it's an interesting question, I don't know the answer, I
have to look into that. Okay, אמרו ליה רבנן לאבימי בריה דרבי
אבהו Amru leih rabanan l'Avimi brei d'Rabbi Abbahu, *Amrei lei rabanan leAvimi
brei deRabbi Abahu*,
so the rabbis said to Avimi, the son of Rabbi Abahu, בעי
מיניה מרבי אבהו *bai minei mi-Rabbi Abahu*. Go ask your dad, go
ask רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abbahu שליח דשליח מהו שליח או לא? Shliach
d'shliach mahu shliach o lo?
Can שליח shliach number two in this scenario make a שליח shliach
or not? Make a שליח shliach. number three. Okay? And I guess
you could have asked in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel as well. Okay?
But here we have the שליח shliach, made a שליח shliach in
front of this בית דין. Beit Din Can that שליח shliach make
another one? אמר להו לא תיבעי לכו. Amar lehu lo tibei l'chu.
You don't need to ask that question. I'm not going to ask
him that; that's obvious. מדקתני Midekatni the משנה Mishna says אינו שליח
אחרון, eino shliach acharon, the final שליח shliach doesn't have to say
בפני נכתב. So why didn't it just say the second שליח? shliach
Why did it say the final one? מכלל דמשוי שליח. Michlal d'mashvei
shliach.
So you see, it said final, it didn't say second. That means
that he can make another שליח shliach, and another one and another
one and so on. As long as you, yes, once you've established
you can pass on the שליחות, shlichus. you can continue to pass
it on. Okay? So אלא כי תיבעי לכו ella ki tibei l'chu
if you want to ask a good question, here's the question you
should be asking: כי משוי שליח בבית דין או אפילו שלא בבית
דין? ki mashvei shliach b'beis din o afilu shelo b'beis din? When
the second שליח shliach, makes שליח shliach number three, does he need
a בית דין Beit Din? or not? Because he doesn't have to
say בפני נכתב, so maybe he can just directly appoint one over.
On the other hand, if his role is being a שליח shliach
of the court, maybe you need a court to appoint the next
שליח. shliach אמרו ליה הא לא מיבעיא
לן,
Amru leih ha
lo mibayei lan, they said to him, that isn't a question.
ומדקתני—everyone's U'midekatni debating what's a good enough question to ask רבי אבהו—מדקתני
אלא אומר שליח shliach בית דין Beit Din אני.
Since the last שליח, shliach which you have now established for us
means שליח shliach number three or four or five, says I'm a
שליח shliach of the court, so to be a שליח shliach of
a court, you need a court to appoint him. And maybe that's
also why a שליח shliach can make a שליח, shliach, because in
the end, he's not really making a שליח, shliach really the court
is taking the responsibility, I mean the court is making שליח shliach
number three and four, right? So would it be the same, for
example, in the previous משנה? Mishna If it didn't involve a court
and it was in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel, and שליח shliach number
one made שליח shaliach number two? Can two make three and three
make four and four make five? Right? So that's maybe different because
here there's a court involved at every stage and the שליח shaliach
is basically always a direct appointment of appointee of the court. All
right, so let's keep on reading. רב נחמן בר יצחק מתני הכי.
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak matni hachi. So רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak had this version of events. אמרו ליה Amru lei,
רבנן לאבימי בריה דרבי אבהו, the rabbis said to Avimi the son
of רבי אבהו: Rabbi Abbahu: בעי מיניה דרבי אבהו, ba'ei mineih d'Rabbi
Abbahu, ask your dad, ask
רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abbahu. They just started like at a different stage
in the process. They were assuming that שליח shaliach. number two could
make שליח shaliach number three. But כי משוי שליח בבית דין או
שלא בבית דין? ki mashvei shliach b'beis din o shelo b'beis din?
They wanted to know, did it have to have been in a
court or not? אמר להו ותיבעי לכו אי משוי שליח בעלמא? Amar
lehu v'tibei l'chu i mashvei shliach b'alma? So what makes you assume
that number two can make another number three? אמרו ליה הא לא
מיבעיא לן, Amru leih ha lo mibayei lan, they said to him,
no, that wasn't a question for us. דתנן אינו שליח אחרון detnan
eino shliach acharon because it says the last שליח shaliach doesn't have
to say בפני נכתב. מכלל דשליח משוי שליח. Michlal d'shliach mashvei shliach.
So from there it was obvious to us in the משנה that
you can make three and four and five. אלא כי קמיבעיא לן
בבית דין או שלא בבית דין? Ella ki kamibayei lan b'beis din
o shelo b'beis din? In a court or even not a court?
אמר להו הא נמי לא תיבעי לכו. Amar lehu ha nami lo
tibei l'chu. He said to them, then you shouldn't ask then the
second question you shouldn't ask either. דקתני אלא אומר שליח בית דין
אני. Dekatni ella omer shliach beis din ani. You say I'm a
שליח shaliach of the court. So this establishes that a שליח shaliach
two can make three can make four can make five, but it
has to be done in a court. And the interesting question which
the גמרא Gemara is not exploring at this stage is: are those
interrelated? Is the only reason you can keep on going down the
chain because you're really not making the next שליח, shaliach. you're really
handing back the responsibility to a court and the court is making
it? And maybe that changes the dynamic. Okay? But maybe in ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisroel who knows? Maybe it would be different. All right,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רבא שליח בארץ ישראל. Amar Rava shliach b'Eretz Yisroel. So now
the גמרא Gemara turns to that, see, I knew what was coming
up. שליח בארץ ישראל עושה כמה שלוחים. Shliach b'Eretz Yisroel oseh kama
shluchim. It is not limited to חוץ לארץ, chutz l'aretz, it's not
limited to being appointed by the court. Even in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisroel. where it's a private affair of handing over the שליחות, shlichus
you can pass it on from one to the next to the
next. Remember this also helps that you actually have a physical גט,
get right? For רבא Rava that that helps sort of concretize, you
know, the
שליחות. shlichus Okay? Okay. So עושה
כמה שלוחים.
oseh kama
shluchim. And if רש״י Rashi just spells out: ואין הראשון צריך לומר
בפני נכתב והאחרון נמי אין צריך לומר שליח בית דין אני. v'ein
harishon tzarich lomar b'fanai nichtav v'ha'acharon nami ein tzarich lomar shliach beis
din ani. You don't have any of those other requirements of our
משנה. You don't have to say בפני נכתב because it's ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisroel, You don't have to say שליח shaliach בית דין Beit
Din. because it's not involving a בית דין Beit Din, because you're
not saying בפני נכתב. It's all a private affair. And nevertheless, you
can pass it on to two, three, and four and five and
so on. Okay? So either of those processes work. אמר רב אשי,
Amar Rav Ashi, says רב אשי: Rav Ashi: אם מת ראשון בטלו
כולן. im mes rishon batlu kulan. Now we get to an interesting
question. Okay? And now we're dealing with in ארץ ישראל, because where
it's clearly not involving a בית דין. Beit Din, Let's say you
cut the daisy chain at one point. Let's say the first שליח
shaliach dies. Is the second שליח shaliach the שליח shliach of the
first guy or the... Now I think it seems pretty obvious to
us he's the שליח shliach, of the husband. You're passing on the
agency you received from the husband. You don't answer to me, you
answer to the husband, right? But the first statement is very strange
is no, you're ultimately a שליח shliach of the שליח. shliach And
if שליח shliach, number one dies, the other שלוחים shluchim are בטל.
batel. So אם מת ראשון בטלו כולן. im meis rishon batlu kulan.
The גמרא Gemara rejects this. אמר בר רב אשי, Amar bar Rav
Ashi, we have a lot of fathers and sons here, so מר
Mar the son of רב אשי Rav Ashi says, הא דאבא דקטנותא
היא, ha d'abba de'katnusa hee, that that my father said, he was
a kid when he said it. That's not actually true. Okay, אילו
מת, ilu meis, and just imagine disagreeing with your father, אילו מת,
ilu meis, yeah, אילו מת בעל מידי מששא אית בהו? ilu meis
baal midi mashasha is behu?
Look, let's say the husband died. Would the שליחות shlichus still be
around if the husband died? Well, I don't care if the husband
died, I'm only a שליח shliach of guy number one, I'm not
a שליח shliach? of the husband. No! Of course not! Of course
you're a שליח shliach of the husband. If the husband died, you
wouldn't be a שליח. shliach So כולם מכח מאן קאתו? kulam mi'koach
man ka'asu? Who are they all empowered by? Who's the real person,
you know, whose power is being sort of, you know,
operated here? מכח דבעל קאתו. mi'koach d'baal ka'asu. They're coming from the
power of the husband. Okay. איתיה לבעל איתיה לכולהו. isay le'baal isay
le'kulehu.
As long as the husband is alive, I don't care if anybody
else dies. All the שלוחים shluchim are good because ultimately they're just
handing over the agency from of the husband.
Okay. ליתיה לבעל ליתיה לכולהו. leisay le'baal leisay le'kulehu. And if the
husband is dead, I don't care if the other שלוחים shluchim are
alive. You're not, well, I don't care if the husband's dead, I'm
still a שליח shaliach of guy number one, you know? So he
basically says this is silly. Of course you're a שליח of the
person. That person in his own identity has no role here, right?
Once he's just handing you over the agency and now you're responsible
to the husband. Now it is interesting though, because there is a
case where this isn't as obvious. And that's a case of, for
example, the גמרא Gemara before
mentioned שומר שמסר לשומר. shomer she'masar l'shomer. If you give me an
object to watch, and I go ahead and I go and I
give it to דוב Dov to watch, right? Is דוב Dov watching
it for me or is דוב Dov watching it for you? Okay,
so they're actually, there's a whole סוגיא sugya in בבא מציעא Bava
Metzia about that. Okay, there's actually a possibility where I could make
money off of that. You give it to me as a שומר
חנם, shomer chinam, and then I pay דוב Dov to watch it
for me as a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. And then something happens
to the object. So, you know, that's an אונס. oness. So he,
because he's being paid, not an אונס, oness, it's a, whatever, it's
a גניבה, gneiva, it gets stolen. So he as a שומר שכר
shomer sachar is liable, so he pays me for it, but I
as a שומר חנם shomer chinam to you am not liable. So,
anyway, that's a question in the משנה. Okay, as to רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi says, היאך הלה עושה סחורה בפרתו של חבירו. heich hala
oseh schora be'paraso shel chaveiro. Anyway, so there is a case like
that where actually you could be sort of doing somebody else's job
for them, but that's a little different because there it doesn't focus
on power. There it focuses on like an object and who are
you watching the object for as opposed to here, the role of
divorcing the wife is something that only the husband is the relevant
party. So anybody that's empowered to divorce the wife is directly representing
the husband, cannot be representing somebody else. Yes?
If the husband dies, she can't get a גט, get right? Right.
So that's the point. It was just, it was just an absurd
point. It's like, it's all obviously about the husband, right? Who could
you be representing if not the husband?
Okay, it's just a way of saying that. Okay.
ההוא גברא. Hahu gavra. Now we're going to get some stories. ההוא
גברא דשדריה לגיטא לדביתהו. Hahu gavra d'shadreih l'gita l'deveiseihu. A man sent
a גט get to his wife. אמר שליח, Amar shaliach, לא ידענא
לה. lo yadana lah. I don't know who she is. How am
I supposed to go ahead and give it to her? Okay, and
presumably this was in חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, he was going to
have to find a בית דין if he wanted to hand it
over. So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to him, look, זיל
יהביה לאבא בר מניומי. zil yahveih l'Abba bar Minyumi. Look, you know
אבא בר מניומי, Abba bar Minyumi, right? He said, yes, him I
know. Fine. Go give it to him, דאיהו ידע לה, d'ihu yada
lah, he knows my wife, he'll give it to my wife. וליזיל
וליתביה ניהלה, ve'leizil ve'lisveih nihala, and he'll go give it to her.
אתא, Asa, he went to the town, ולא אשכח לאבא בר מניומי.
ve'lo ashkeich l'Abba bar Minyumi. He couldn't find אבא בר מניומי. Abba
bar Minyumi. אשכחיה לרבי אבהו ולרבי חנינא בר פפא ורבי יצחק נפחא.
Ashkeichei l'Rabbi Abbahu u'l'Rabbi Chanina bar Pappa ve'Rabbi Yitzchak Napcha. He found
these three rabbis. ויתיב רב ספרא גבייהו, ve'yasiv Rav Safra gabayeihu, by
the way, רב ספרא Rav Safra was also there. אמרו ליה, and
they said to him, look, so he said, what should I do?
I got to give it to the wife, he told me to
give it to אבא בר מניומי, Abba bar Minyumi, I can't find
him. Listen, מסור מילך קמן, mesor mileich kaman, give your words over
in front of us. It's interesting, it echoes the phrase מילי לא
מימסרן לשליח. Okay, but this is the מילים, milim, the words that
he's giving over here are בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. Testify to us
בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם דידן, deedan, and then we as the משנה
teaches us will appoint אבא בר מניומי Abba bar Minyumi when we
find him. דכי אתי אבא בר מניומי ונספניה ליה וליזיל וליתביה ניהלה,
de'chi asay Abba bar Minyumi ve'nispineih lei ve'leizil ve'lisveih nihala, when אבא
בר מניומי Abba bar Minyumi shows up,
we'll give it to him and he'll go give it to her.
It's perfect. Okay? You do what the משנה says, say בפני נכתב,
appoint us as your agent, we'll go ahead and we'll appoint אבא
בר מניומי Abba bar Minyumi when we find him. אמר להו רב
ספרא, Amar lehu Rav Safra, so רב ספרא Rav Safra who was
sitting on the sidelines said to these three who are now serving
as a בית דין, והא שליח שלא ניתן לגירושין הוא. ve'ha shaliach
she'lo nitan l'geirushin hu. Why,
I don't understand how this can work. The first שליח cannot... power
you. Why can he not empower you? Because he himself was not
empowered to deliver the גט. get He was only empowered to hand
it over to אבא בר מניומי. Abba bar Minyomi. So he is
assuming that the ability to transfer the responsibility to a בית דין
of giving the גט get is something that you have to be
fully in the role of husband, fully in the position to give
the גט yourself. But if you're only in the position to hand
it off to אבא בר מניומי, Abba bar Minyomi, then you can't...
Now, why can't you hand that power to בית דין? I have
the power to appoint אבא בר מניומי, Abba bar Minyomi, you appoint
אבא בר מניומי Abba bar Minyomi for me. But anyway he's assuming
now if you're not in the position as a husband then you
cannot appoint, you know, a בית דין to take that responsibility of
the גט from you. It would be interesting if he would say
could he presumably also just can't appoint a שליח to do it
for him? The whole this gets back to the question under what
circumstances can you transfer the agency? So he assumes you have to
be fully empowered in the act in order to be able to
transfer the agency.
So אכספו, Ikhsifu, so all these rabbis were embarrassed that they didn't
think about that point. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava said,
כפניו רב ספרא לתלתא רבנן סמוכי, Kaphinei Rav Safra l'tlata rabanan smukhei,
רב ספרא Rav Safra sort of showed up these three big rabbis,
these rabbis who have סמיכה, smicha, these ordained rabbis, and he really
showed them up. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, so רב אשי
Rav Ashi says, במאי כפניו רב ספרא לתלתא רבנן סמוכי... Bemai kaphinei
Rav Safra l'tlata rabanan smukhei... I'm sorry... אמר רב... אמר רב אשי.
Amar Rav Ashi. אמר רבא. Amar Rava. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav
Ashi, במאי כפניו, bemai kaphinei, what type of a, as we would
say in yeshiva, what type of a שלוג-אפ shlog-up was that? What
type of a... why did he embarrass them? Why? What type of
that wasn't a challenge? מי אמר ליה אבא בר מניומי ולא את?
Mi amar lei Abba bar Minyomi velo at? I don't get it.
He didn't say I only want אבא בר מניומי Abba bar Minyomi
to deliver the גט. אבא בר מניומי Abba bar Minyomi I was
helping him out because he didn't know who my wife was, but
if he were able to bump into my wife and discovered that
that was my wife, and אבא בר מניומי Abba bar Minyomi told
him that that was my wife, I wouldn't have had a problem
for him to give the גט to my wife. So he was
empowered to deliver the גט to my wife, I wasn't telling him
he couldn't, right? I was advising him to find אבא בר מניומי,
Abba bar Minyomi, but that didn't say that he was not empowered.
So he was ניתן לגירושין, nitan l'geirushin, he was empowered to deliver
the גט and therefore he could make a בית דין. איכא דאמרי,
Ika d'amrei, we'll just end with this, there's another version of
this, אמר רבא כפניו רב ספרא לתלתא רבנן סמוכי בטעותא. Amar Rava
kaphinei Rav Safra l'tlata rabanan smukhei b'tauta. רבא Rava himself recognized it
was an error. He שלוג'ד shlog'd them up and they were embarrassed,
but they should be embarrassed that they were embarrassed, okay? Because the
whole thing was an error. It wasn't a good challenge. אמר רב
אשי מאי טעותא? Amar Rav Ashi mai tauta? Why, what was now
there's two ways to read רב אשי. Rav Ashi. I'm going to
read it תוספות'ס Tosafos's way. There's a מחלוקת ראשונים machlokes Rishonim how
to read רב אשי. Rav Ashi. This the way I'm about to
read it is completely consistent with what we just said. He said
מאי טעותא, mai tauta, why was it an error? Here's why it
was an error.
מי אמר ליה אבא מניומי ולא את mi amar lei Abba Minyomi
velo at because he didn't say only אבא בר מניומי Abba bar
Minyomi and not you. So it was he was totally fine with
this guy being the one to give it. That's the way to
read it that it's coming to the same conclusion. But the version
we have is actually that רב אשי Rav Ashi says it wasn't
an error. מאי טעותא, Mai tauta, why was it an error? מאי
אמר ליה, Mai amar lei, what did he say to him? He
said to him אבא בר מניומי ולא את. Abba bar Minyomi velo
at. So רב אשי Rav Ashi is actually ending by saying no,
in the end of the day he only wanted אבא בר מניומי
Abba bar Minyomi to do it. But anyway a better read, more
I would say a more logical read just in thinking about the
circumstances, is that in principle he would be okay with this guy
giving the גט to his wife as well, so he was ניתן
לגירושין. nitan l'geirushin. But besides the circumstances, the principle is interesting because
the principle the גמרא Gemara says is that if he was only
appointed to give it over to another שליח, wasn't fully empowered to
give it himself, then he also his ability to give over the
power to oversee the גט to the בית דין, he doesn't have
that power because you have to in order to give it over
the full responsibility to a בית דין, you need to be fully
empowered to give the גט yourself. The interesting question is, and I'll
end with this, but if he wasn't empowered to give it himself,
what type of power what was he a שליח at all? Basically
what, he's a שליח to give it to אבא בר מניומי? Abba
bar Minyomi? Who needs him? I can send it in the mail
to אבא בר מניומי. Abba bar Minyomi. I'm really only appointing אבא
בר מניומי Abba bar Minyomi as my שליח, really what's happening is
I'm appointing אבא בר מניומי Abba bar Minyomi in not in his
presence. Right, think about it, let's say I only said you cannot
give the גט to my wife, you have to give it to
אבא בר מניומי, Abba bar Minyomi, he's going to give the גט
to my wife. Are you a שליח or are you just a
mail service? Right, what type of שליחות is it to give it
to, do you need a שליחות to appoint a שליח? Or can
you appoint a שליח שלא בפניו, shelo befanav, right, without his knowledge?
Well, and without his knowledge. But if I basically go ahead I
write him a letter and I'm saying enclosed in this letter please
find this, please deliver to my wife, well you could say that's
like a דיבור. dibur.
Well that's the question. Can you appoint... eventually he'll find out, you'll
inform him of it. But are you a, do I have to
directly appoint him and you're my שליח to do the act of
appointing? Or can I appoint him שלא בפניו shelo befanav and then
you're just a mail service, you know. Can you appoint a eventually
he'll find out, you'll inform
him of it. But are you asking do I have to directly
appoint him and you're my שליח to be to do the act
of appointing? Or can I appoint him שלא בפניו shelo befanav and
then you're just a mail service? And so that is not clear
from this גמרא. Gemara. All right.